The barn was very large. It was very old. It smelled of hay and it smelled of
manure. It smelled of the perspiration of tired horses and the wonderful sweet
breath of patient cows. It often had a sort of peaceful smell, as though
nothing bad could happen ever again in the world.
It smelled of grain and of harness dressing and of axle grease and of
rubber boots and of new rope.
And whenever the cat was given a fish head to eat, the barn would smell of
fish, but mostly it smelled of hay, for there was always hay in the great loft
up overhead, and there was always hay being pitched down to the cows and the
horses and the sheep.
The barn was pleasantly warm in winter when the animals spent most of their
time indoors, and it was pleasantly cool in summer when the big doors stood wide
open to the breeze.
The barn had stalls on the main floor for the workh horses, tie-ups on the
main floor for the cows, a sheepfold down below for the sheep, a pig pin down
below for Wilbur, and it was full of all sorts of things that you find in barns.
ladders, grindstones, pitchforks, monkey wrenches, sthes, lawnmowers, snow
shovels, axe handles, milk pales, water buckets, empty grain sacks, and rusty
rat traps. It was the kind of barn that swallows like to build their nests in.
It was the kind of barn that children like to play in. And the whole thing was
owned by Fern's uncle, Mr. Homer L.
Zuckerman.
Wilbur's new home was in the lower part of the barn, directly underneath the
cows. Mr. Zuckerman knew that a manure pile is a good place to keep a young
pig. Pigs need warmth, and it was warm and comfortable down there in the barn
cellar on the south side.
Fern came almost every day to visit him.
She found an old milking stool that had been discarded, and she placed the stool
in the sheepfold next to Wilbur's pen.
Here she sat quietly during the long afternoons, thinking and listening and watching Wilbur.
The sheep soon got to know her and trust her. So did the geese who lived with the
sheep. All the animals trusted her. She was so quiet and friendly. Mr. Zuckerman
did not allow her to take Wilbur out, and he did not allow her to get into the
pig pin, but he told Fern that she could sit on the stool and watch Wilbur as
long as she wanted to. It made her happy just to be near the pig, and it made
Wilbur happy to know that she was sitting there right outside his pen. But
he never had any fun. No walks, no rides, no swims.
One afternoon in June, when Wilbur was almost 2 months old, he wandered out
into his small yard outside the barn.
Fern had not arrived for her usual visit. Wilbur stood in the sun, feeling
lonely and bored. "There's never anything to do around here," he thought.
He walked slowly to his food trough and sniffed to see if anything had been
overlooked at lunch. He found a small strip of potato skin and ate it. His
back itched, so he leaned against the fence and rubbed against the boards.
When he tired of this, he walked indoors, climbed to the top of the
manure pile, and sat down. He didn't feel like going to sleep. He didn't feel
like digging. He was tired of standing still, tired of lying down. "I'm less
than 2 months old and I'm tired of living," he said. He walked out to the
yard again. "When I'm out here," he said, "there's no place to go but in.
When I'm indoors, there's no place to go but out in the yard."
That's where you're wrong, my friend. My friend, said a voice. Wilbur looked
through the fence and saw the goose standing there. You don't have to stay
in that dirty little dirty little dirty little yard, said the goose, who talked
rather fast. "One of the boards is loose. Push on it. Push push push on it
and come on out." "What?" said Wilbur.
Say it slower.
At the risk of repeating myself, said the goose, I suggest that you come on
out. It's wonderful out here. Did you say a board was loose? That I did that I
did, said the goose. Wilbur walked up to the fence and saw that the goose was
right. One board was loose. He put his head down, shut his eyes, and pushed
The board gave way. In a minute, he had squeezed through the fence and was
standing in the long grass outside his yard.
The goose chuckled. "How does it feel to be free?" she asked. "I
like it," said Wilbur. "That is I guess I like it." Actually, Wilbur felt queer
to be outside his fence with nothing between him and the big world. "Where do
you think I'd better go?" "Anywhere you like, anywhere you like," said the
goose. Go down through the orchard. Root up the sod. Go down through the garden.
Dig up the radishes. Root up everything.
Eat grass. Look for corn. Look for oats.
Run all over. Skip and dance. Jump and prance. Go down through the orchard and
stroll in the woods.
The world is a wonderful place when you're young. I can see that," replied
Wilbur. He gave a jump in the air, twirled, ran a few steps, stopped,
looked all around, sniffed the smells of afternoon, and then set off walking down
through the orchard.
Pausing in the shade of an apple tree, he put his strong snout into the ground
and began pushing, digging, and rooting.
He felt very happy. He had plowed up quite a piece of ground before anyone
noticed him. Mrs. Zuckerman was the first to see him. She saw him from the
kitchen window and she immediately shouted for the men.
Homer, she cried. Pigs out. Larvy, pigs out. Homer, Larvy, pigs out. He's down
there under that apple tree. Now the trouble starts, thought Wilbur. Now I'll
catch it. The goose heard the racket and she too started hollering. Run, run, run
downhill. Make for the woods. The woods, she shouted to Wilbur. They'll never
never never catch you in the woods.
The cocker spaniel heard the commotion and he ran out from the barn to join the
chase. Mr. Zuckerman heard and he came out of the machine shed where he was
mending a tool. Larvy the hired man heard the noise and came up from the
asparagus patch where he was pulling weeds. Everybody walked toward Wilbur
and Wilbur didn't know what to do. The woods seemed a long way off and anyway
he had never been down there in the woods and wasn't sure he would like it.
Get around behind him, Lurvby, said Mr.
Zuckerman, and drive him toward the barn. And take it easy. Don't rush him.
I'll go and get a bucket of slops. The news of Wilbur's escape spread rapidly
among the animals on the place. Whenever any creature broke loose on Zuckerman's
farm, the event was of great interest to the others. The goose shouted to the
nearest cow that Wilbur was free.
And soon all the cows knew. Then one of the cows told one of the sheep,
and soon all the sheep knew.
The lambs learned about it from their mothers.
The horses in their stalls in the barn pricricked up their ears when they heard
the goose hollering. And soon the horses had caught on to what was happening.
"Wilbur's out," they said. Every animal stirred and lifted its head and became
excited to know that one of his friends had got free and was no longer penned up
or tied fast.
Wilbur didn't know what to do or which way to run. It seemed as though
everybody was after him. If this is what it's like to be free, he thought, I
believe I'd rather be pinned up in my own yard.
The cocker spaniel was sneaking up on him from one side. Lurvy, the hired man,
was sneaking up on him from the other side. Mrs. Zuckerman stood ready to head
him off if he started for the garden.
And now Mr. Zuckerman was coming down toward him, carrying a pale.
This is really awful, thought Wilbur.
Why doesn't Fern come? He began to cry.
The goose took command and began to give orders. Don't just stand there, Wilbur.
Dodge about. Dodge about, cried the goose. Skip around. Run toward me. Slip
in and out. In and out. In and out. Make for the woods. Twist and turn.
The cocker spaniel sprang for Wilbur's hind leg. Wilbur jumped and ran. Larvy
reached out and grabbed. Mrs. Zuckerman screamed at Lurvy. The goose cheered for
Wilbur. Wilbur dodged between Lurvy's legs. Lurvy missed Wilbur and grabbed
the spananiel instead. "Nicely done!
Nicely done!" cried the goose. "Try it again. Try it again.
Run down him, suggested the cows. Run toward me, yelled the gander. Run up hill, cried
the sheep. Turn and twist, honked the goose. Jump and dance, said the rooster.
Look out for Lurvy, called the cows. Look out for Zuckermanmen, yelled the gender. Watch
out for the dog, cried the sheep. Listen to me, listen to me, screamed the goose.
Poor Wilbur was dazed and frightened by this hullaloo.
He didn't like being the center of all this fuss. He tried to follow the
instructions his friends were giving him, but he couldn't run downhill and
uphill at the same time, and he couldn't turn and twist when he was jumping and
dancing, and he was crying so hard he could barely see anything that was
happening. After all, Wilbur was a very young pig, not much more than a baby, really.
He wished Fern were there to take him in her arms and comfort him. When he looked
up and saw Mr. Zuckerman standing quite close to him, holding a pale of warm
slops, he felt relieved.
He lifted his nose and sniffed. The smell was delicious.
warm milk, potato skins, wheat middlings, Kellogg's corn flakes, and a
popover left from the Zuckermanman's breakfast. "Come, pig," said Mr.
Zuckerman, tapping the pale. "Come, pig!" Wilbur took a step toward the pale.
"No, no, no," said the goose. "It's the old pale trick, Wilbur. Don't fall for
it. Don't fall for it. He's trying to lure you back into captivity. He's
appealing to your stomach. Wilbur didn't care. The food smelled appetizing. He
took another step toward the pale. Pig, pig, said Mr. Zuckerman in a kind voice
and began walking slowly toward the barnyard, looking all about him
innocently as if he didn't know that a little white pig was following along behind him.
"You will be sorry, sorry, sorry," called the goose. Wilbur didn't care. He
kept walking toward the pale of slops.
You'll miss your freedom, honked the goose. An hour of freedom is worth a
barrel of slops. Wilbur didn't care.
When Mr. Zuckerman reached the pig pen, he climbed over the fence and poured the
slops into the trough. Then he pulled the loose board away from the fence so
that there was a wide hole for Wilbur to walk through.
"Reconsider! Reconsider!" cried the goose. Wilbur paid no attention. He
stepped through the fence into his yard.
He walked to the trough and took a long drink of slops, sucking in the milk
hungrily and chewing the popover.
It was good to be home again.
While Wilbur ate, Lurvy fetched a hammer and some eight penny nails and nailed
the board in place. Then he and Mr.
Zuckerman leaned lazily on the fence and Mr. Zuckerman scratched Wilbur's back with a stick.
"He's quite a pig," said Lurvy. "Yes, he'll make a good pig," said Mr.
Zuckerman. Wilbur heard the words of praise. He felt the warm milk inside his
stomach. He felt the pleasant rubbing of the stick along his itchy back. He felt
peaceful and happy and sleepy. This had been a tiring afternoon.
It was still only about 4:00, but Wilbur was ready for bed. "I'm really too young
to go out into the world alone," he thought as he lay down.
Chapter 4.
loneliness.